Hi, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to
be looking at the pH scale.
So pH is all about the measure of
acidity of hydrogen ions in an aqueous
solution, meaning that whenever we have
any type of solution that you might
have around the household or in the
chemistry lab, they have a pH to them.
Meaning they have so much acidity to them.
So this is all about the
potential of hydrogen.
So how much hydrogen ions do
we have within a solution?
So if I, for pH, this is a scale
that is a very simple range.
It goes from zero to 14.
It is a simple scale.
So that way we can easily be able to
relate it to normal numbers that you
can count on your hand, hands and toes.
So if we have a scale like this,
the way that it generally works
is it goes from zero to 14.
Meaning that we have a range
of how acidic something can be.
So a pH of 7 is usually where that
is, where we all want to start.
That is where we have water.
That is just a normal pH of 7.
Meaning this is neutral.
So you can drink, drinking
water and it is fine.
generally safe for you to do.
Now, as you go into the more acidic side,
that is when the pH is going less than 7.
So the lower that number, the
more acidic something is, meaning
the higher that that hydrogen ion
concentration is, within a solution.
So if you kind of change some of
those, some of those things that you
might kind of recognize is if you go
around like a pH of 4, pH of 3, those
are things like soda, juices that
you commonly find at the supermarket.
Those are very acidic.
They're harsher on the
stomach when you drink them.
Other things that are a little harsher are
things like coffee, for example, right?
Coffee also has a very, very low pH.
Some other examples that you might
find in your general household are like
lemon juice and vinegar, things that
you commonly use in cooking, right?
A lot of times these are acidic
ingredients that we see in salad
dressings that give us that sour taste.
They help break down different ingredients
and unlock a bunch of different flavors.
Some other things that we also
have is a really low pH, a pH of
one that is your stomach acid.
So gastric juices.
So when you eat something,
it travels through your body.
And eventually it comes down to the
stomach, which will break down foods even
more by causing all those bonds to break.
Some other things that you might
come across as battery acid, right?
If you have to change your car battery out
in that there are different, very, very
common things that you always see, right?
PH of five and six bananas and
milk, all your household chemicals.
As we go in the other direction, this
is increasing alkalinity, meaning that
the base portion is getting stronger.
Bases are always represented by hydroxide,
so OH is dissociating off of a solution.
So when we go in this direction,
things like eggs, baking soda, milk
and magnesia are also some common
things that you find in a household.
As you go farther down, more things that
are cleaning products that you use to,
to, uh, to clean your home, like ammonia,
maybe soap, bleach, drain cleaner.
These are higher pHs because they
are something that's going to
break down a lot of those oils
and fats and things like that.
So this is what we're going to be looking
into and trying to understand how this
scale works as we go from a 0 to 14.
And what different calculations might
apply to you within your chemistry
class, or your introductory chemistry,
or your general chemistry course.
And I hope that this helps, please
feel free to like and subscribe and
stay tuned for examples to come.
Hi, and welcome back.
So with this one, what we're going
to look at is first, let's diagnose
what is an acid, What is a base?
When it comes to pH and pOH, we can, we
can go and look at a variety of different
acids and bases that vary in strength.
For today's little mini lecture,
we're gonna mainly be looking
at strong acids and bases.
What does that mean?
Well, if we want to look at the
basic example of an acid, let's say
if I have something like HCl which
is one of our common strong acids.
If that is to dissociate in
water, what exactly does that
make when it breaks down?
We want to look at what ions
make this ionic compound up.
And one of those things that it
makes up is H plus and Cl minus,
which are our two halves of the
compound that are here, right?
So those are our two pieces.
Now why is that important to us?
Well, this H plus portion.
is what you are going to
be measuring using pH.
So pH is where that comes from.
Now, when it comes to a base, this
is going to be a little bit different
when we are looking at a base.
So base is when we, let's say if
we take something like NaOH, Now
the thing that makes these acids
and bases is it's H and then O.
So oh, is really where you see that
base characteristic is coming from.
So once again, when we put this in
water, we're gonna see that this is gonna
break down into, its two ion compounds.
So sodium is going to break off and
hydroxide is going to break off as well.
So we'll have na plus and hydroxide.
Now, when this is breaking off the OH
where we can measure pH, however, there's
no hydrogens that are being generated.
So what we're going to be talking
about is a different type of
pH, instead it's going to be.
P O H is what we're going to be talking
about in a few, in a little bit ahead.
So the first one though, pH.
So in order to measure pH, we're going
to be using the following formula, which
is pH is equal to negative log of H plus.
Now, whenever, when we are dealing
with this, something when for a lot
of chemistry students, you might
not know how to use log function.
Or you're not used to it.
So let's talk about what exactly is a log.
What does that represent?
Well, a log is short for a logarithm,
which is something, which is a function
that you can find on your calculator.
It should say L O G is the button
that you were looking for, not L N.
So keep that in mind.
They are two different functions.
So we're looking for a
logarithmic function.
And with this one, these are mathematical
functions that tell how many times
The base is multiplied by itself
to reach the number that you have.
So what exactly does that mean?
So it's not the log as in a log that
you find in the woods, but instead
it is a mathematical function.
So every log, you generally, you see
that there is a little number next to it.
Okay.
With your calculator, it is automatically
assumed that it is a log base 10,
which is the normal log system.
However, some calculators, you can
actually put what type of log you want.
So pay attention.
If you see a little tiny box next
to the log function, that's telling
you, you need to input a number there
to put 10 for these calculations.
So if I have, let's say a thousand here.
Well, what it's asking is how many
times would I have to multiply
this space to fit into a thousand?
So if you think of a thousand,
right, if I do 10 times, 10 times,
10, the 10 times 10 is a hundred,
a hundred times, 10, a thousand.
You had to do that three times.
So that tells you that your
log is 10 in the, or sorry,
your log is 3 in this example.
So then this is really
where pH is coming from.
So it's a 10 based scale, meaning
that the concentrations are being
that this is a negative value up
in our, in our formula up here.
These are going to be very,
very tiny numbers that we're
going to be dealing with.
So the concentration is small and
it has so much, um, uh, capability
here for such a small number.
Okay.
This is where we're gonna go into
our next and upcoming example.
Hi.
And here we go.
Let's do this example.
So if we have the following question,
a student prepares a 2.1 times 10 to
negative four molar solution of HCL.
So with this type of formula, when we
are using the pH equation, this is always
gonna be relating directly to the negative
log of the concentration of h plus.
Meaning, when we have concentration,
those square brackets are always
telling you about molarity.
So, we're going to always be in moles
over liters when we are looking at those
units, for either H plus or OH minus.
So, being that HCl is a strong
acid, it's going to completely
dissociate into H plus.
So, those concentrations are
going to be equal to each other.
So the concentration of HCL is going
to be equal to the concentration of
h plus, and this is for strong acids.
So keep that in mind.
That's something,
there's six strong acids.
That'll be its own video, and
that is one thing to remember.
So when we are doing this, what we're
going to do is we'll take the pH, it'll
be the negative log of 2.1 times 10
to the negative four molar, and that's
going to be in the parentheses here.
Now, when you put that into
your calculator, what you're
going to be getting is 3.
677 is your number.
So that's telling you how many
times negative or 10 is fitting
into this calculation, um, when
we are trying to calculate this.
Now how do we do sig figs?
Well, sig fig is always something
we got to make sure we are
accurate about in the lab.
So when it comes to
the amount of sig figs.
Um, it's equal to the number of decimal
places in your pH value, so, and also
what you had in your original number.
So if we had in the original
calculation, we had two sig figs.
So what that means is that we also
are going to have two sig figs in
our decimal places in our pH value.
So when we convert this,
this is going to become 3.
68 is going to be our final one.
Okay.
Thank you.
So it's all about the decimal
places when it comes to significant
figures for these examples.
So if I continue this problem
and I ask you, Alright, what
is the H plus concentration?
And then you might say like, well,
wait a minute, didn't you say
earlier that HCl is equal to H plus?
And you are right.
So that what that means
is that number is 2.
1 times 10 to the negative
4 molar is my concentration.
However, there's a formula to
go back in order to go from pH
to your original concentration.
So that formula is a little bit different.
So what we are going to be doing here is
if we have our pH formula, we have to take
an inverse log to go to concentration.
So an inverse log is
simply the following thing.
So if I have my hydrogen
plus concentration, that's
going to be equal to the 10.
to the power of negative pH, and
that is our other equation that we
are, that we are going to use in
order to find the concentration.
So if we use that here, what we can
pretty much do is if I do um, the
same calculation, let's say you didn't
know that it was a strong acid, and
you didn't know how to do it, Then
we would go 10 to the negative 3.
68, and that will give us an answer of 2.
1 times 10 to the negative 4 molar for
our concentration of H for this problem.
So you can go back and forth
between those two values.
And that's how you do pH and find
the concentration of H So if pH
tells you the strength of acidity,
then pOH must tell you the strength
of alkalinity, meaning that we can
do the same calculations for pOH.
So if I have a base, we can figure
out how strong that base is instead
of it being represented by an acid.
Remember, these are two different species.
They're related to each other, being that
they can neutralize one another, but it
all depends on what example are you given.
Are you given an acid
or are you given a base?
Because that's what your calculation
is going to be referencing.
So if I have the following problem that
says the pOH of ammonium hydroxide is 8.
6, calculate the molarity
of OH minus ions.
So, this is the same formulas, POH
is equal to the negative log of
hydroxide concentration, or if you
want to take the inverse to find
the concentration, hydroxide is
equal to 10 to the negative POH.
So being that we want to find
concentration, we're going to
use the formula on the right
hand side, which is in yellow.
So, with that, what we are going to do
is we are going to take our formula.
We are going to be solving for our
hydroxide concentration, so we'll
take that oh minus, and that's going
to be equal to 10 to the negative
POH, so 10 to the negative 8.6.
And what that's going to tell us is
the concentration of hydroxide in
solution, which is going to be 2.5
times 10 to the negative nine molar.
of hydroxide that is within our solution.
So, and that is how we would
go about solving for molarity.
Now, when it comes to both pH
and pOH, there's another, there's
a relationship between them.
They are bound together.
So, if I know my pOH, I can
also calculate what my pH is.
So, pH and pOH, if you add them
together, it's always going
to equal 14 at 25 degrees C.
So at standard temperatures.
So being that if we know our, our
value, what we can simply do is we
can rearrange this formula to solve
for, let's say pH and find out exactly
what the pH and how much hydrogen
ion there is in the solution as well.
Being that all these are
in a solution of water.
So being that this problem, I had
14 and then I had my pOH was 8.
6.
We can quickly find what our
concentration is of our pH, which in
this case we would have a pH of Of 5.
4 would be our pH, which tells you
that even though this is a basic
solution, it is a really weak base.
It's not that strong of a base or
not that high of a concentration that
we have is a very low concentration.
So being that the solution is
slightly more acidic than basic.
In summary, what does all this tell us?
Let's look at how all the formulas work.
So originally, if we started
from a concentration of H
we can convert that to pH.
In order to convert that, we
needed to use the negative log
of H in order to convert that.
If you wanted to go backwards,
we can do that as well, where
we take the inverse of a log, so
that would be 10 to the minus 10.
pH to go.
Let's make that a little bit
bolder before we do that.
So we can always go back here
if we needed to.
Now, in order to connect pH and
POH, we can do that as well.
So we can always have an
equation between both of these.
So if we want to go to POH,
that was simply, uh, pH plus.
the pOH is equal to 14.
So you can bridge
between those two values.
Now if we wanted to do our last one, let's
say if we had hydroxide here, we can also
bridge the gap between these as well.
So if I want to go to hydroxide, we
could once again take the 10 to the
negative pOH to go over to hydroxide.
Or if we wanted to convert, Back
to pH, we could find the negative
log of OH to convert back.
So it's a cycle.
So how do we connect the last one?
We didn't talk about that,
but there's a simple, there's
a formula for that as well.
So, if we wanted to link them, this
has to do with the properties of
water, which is another formula
for another video in another time.
But just to show you what it is, it is Kw
is equal to, um, the concentration of H
plus times the concentration of OH minus.
So when KW is equal to 10 to the minus
14, so it's an equilibrium constant.
So in our future videos on equilibrium,
and especially on acid base equilibrium,
we'll bring that into the fold.
So these are how you can convert
going between acids and bases,
so that way if you need to do any
of these different calculations.
You can use these in your chemistry
class to hopefully be able to succeed
and get an A and do really well.
Thank you so much for hanging
out and watching this video.
I hope that it helped and please like
and subscribe for more to come and
please refer these to as many people as
possible that need help with chemistry.
I'm here for you, and this has been Dr.
Dan, and I hope to see
you again in the future.
Bye now.